# Abizeyimana Victor

PRwanda ■svicky.shema@gmail.com □+250789032290 ■ in/victor-abizeyimana-6a710910a/ ▲ https://victor-abz.com

### **SUMMARY**

A problem-solving software engineer with over 6 years of experience developing financial software in a variety of industries, primarily finance and government services. I am driven to collaborate with remote and local teams all over the world to design, build, and continuously improve processes using scalable solutions. simply, I Collaborate, Design, Build, and Improve.

#### **EXPERIENCE**

## Software Project Manager

## Ministry of Health

July 2021 - Present, Rwanda

- Led the development and implementation of a new software system, including requirements gathering, project planning, resource allocation, and quality assurance.
- Managed all aspects of the project, from development to delivery, and successfully delivered the project on time and within budget.

## Senior Software Developer

Benefactors

July 2020 - February 2022, Kigali, Rwanda

- Led the development and rollout of a new software product, working with a cross-functional team to design, build, test, and deploy the product.
- Wrote efficient, reliable, and easy to maintain codes, and collaborated with other developers to share knowledge and expertise.
- Troubleshot and fixed software defects, and provided support to users.
- · Acted as a mentor to junior developers, sharing knowledge and helping them to grow and develop their skills.
- Contributed to the development of company standards and best practices.

#### Software Engineer

#### Andela

November 2019 - April 2020, Rwanda, Nigeria, Kenya, and Uganda

- Developed a system for managing company travel. This involves travel requests, budget preparation, and approval by managers.
- Implemented a scalable solution for handling user authentication and authorization with OAuth2 and a custom JSON web token.
- Developed a microservice architecture for a new product line in Node.js and React that handles all the communication with backend services.

## Co-Founder & CTO

Inepu

July 2017 - June 2020, Kigali, Rwanda

- · Conceptualized, designed, and developed a Learn Management System with Integrated Lesson plan and certification.
- · Designed, Deployed, and monitored a software hosting system managing more than 5TB of traffic daily.
- Deployed a content delivery network for high-traffic websites.

## Consultant Software Developer

#### **T-Kay Investment**

January 2015 - May 2017, Kigali, Remote

- I've extended solutions to various agencies, design studios and also taken on solo projects. I improved processes and provided solutions primarily in the realms of Software Development, design, Communication Materials such as Videos and graphics, and project management.
- · Wrote functional and design specifications for various software products and developed prototypes as well as performed unit testing.
- Managed software development life cycle and conducted risk assessment and mitigation.

## **PROJECTS**

# Rosling - Financial Management Software

Benefactors

- In 2020, I designed and developed a robust system for benefactors, a non-deposit financial institution. The system equipped benefactors with various modules such as loan applications management, Loan disbursement, monitoring, and fees calculation. The app includes strict validation features and user validation from application approval to the amount being disbursed. It features also rich dashboards on loan performance. As well as a simple AI robot to help track loan applicant performance on external systems such as other outside loans and Public tenders.
- I migrated big datasets from the old google sheet-based system to a new system without business disruption and to onboard the team members without a hiccup.
- Currently, The project manages more than 2.4 Billion Rwf extended to more than 150 SMEs.

#### Midas Loan Dashboards

PesaChoice • November 2022 - January 2022

• Lead development of a feature Rich dashboard for PesaChoice, the dashboard allows them to view business metrics in real-time such as loan performance. The System involves predictive analytics to predict trends based on historical data which gives an early warning system to pesaChoice. I lead a team of developers, gather requirements, and supervise the project to stays on budget and on time.

#### Loan Management System

PesaChoice • June 2022 - December 2022

- Designed a loan management system for PesaChoice. The system extends loans to various employees through an existing Payroll system. I lead a team to design, deploy and maintain the system using agile methodology. Testing the product using Chai, Mocha, and Jest as well automatic deployments using CI/CD.
- The loan software actively helps PesaChoice to streamline and automate loan origination, processing, and supervising payments.
- The software also helps to keep track of the employee loans and repayment schedules.

## Medical Doctor Saving Management System

Ministry of Health • July 2021 - December 2021

• The project implemented for the Ministry of Health(MoH) aimed to increase retention of medical doctors and other health workers by promoting saving and extending low-interest loans to them. This platform manages the monthly savings of each healthcare professional and helps on managing loans origination, disbursement, and collection efforts. My role involved the formulation of a detailed project plan, coordination, implementation, and supervision of the software design specifications and development. currently, it manages more than 10,000 Medical professionals with around 5bn Rwf savings.

#### ML Based Credit Scoring

Pesa Choice • June 2021 - December 2022

- I designed and developed an ML-based credit scoring system for PesaChoice. The ML-based system allows PesaChoice to control its risk exposure through the selective allocation of credit based on the statistical analysis of historical customer data.
- The system correctly identifies high-risk customers with a high degree of accuracy of around 89%, which helps the company to better manage its credit risk.
- The system helps the company to improve its customer service by allowing it to provide credit to more customers. The number of customers served weekly increased by more than 5% since its deployment in January 2022.

#### Virtual Sales Data Controller

Benefactors • January 2021 - Present

- In 2021, I lead a team of developers and project managers in the design and deployment of a Virtual Sales Data Controller(VSDC) for Benefactors. The goal of this project launched an invoicing system that provides a cost-effective tool to enable SMEs to comply with tax regulations requiring EBM(Electronic Billing Machine) invoices on all sales and provide the BeneFactors team with a sales history of SMEs prequalify them for working capital loans.
- I led the development team of 4 developers through requirements gathering, design, development, and testing using Agile Methodology. I also ensured that we delivered on time and within budget by conducting necessary scrum ceremonies.

#### **EDUCATION**

#### **Bachelor of Business Administration**

Honors in Finance • University of Rwanda • Rwanda • 2014

## Math, Physics and Computer Science

ES Kanombe • Kigali, Rwanda • 2010

## **CERTIFICATIONS**

# Software Development

Andela • 2020

Certified in Modern software development practice

# **Project Management**

Global Enterprise Experience • 2017

Certified in a standardized and evolving set of project management principles

#### **SKILLS**

Agile Methodology, Human-Centered Design, Software Product Design, Test-Driven Development with MOcha, Chai, and Jest. Continuos Development(CI/CD) Frontend: React, HTML, CSS, Javascript, Php Backend: NodeJS, Python, Django DevOps: Deployment, Server monitoring